Hello, brilliant minds
and future physicians.
My name is Brian
Kalfanovich. I am one of your
academic medicine
scholars, and I am happy
to be delivering this
lecture on renal physiology,
regulation of sodium
and water excretion.
Specifically, we're going
to be looking at how the
kidney is defending blood
volume and osmolality. I
would like to thank Dr.
Ascari for his input, as well
as allowing me to deliver
the lecture for you
guys, as well as Dr. Goldstein
for her input as well.
This lecture is really
fascinating as it covers
some pinnacle topics within
internal medicine, and
if there are any questions
at any point, please do
not hesitate to contact
me by email at any time.
Here are your learning
objectives for today's
lecture. I implore you to
pause and read through these
thoroughly, and then at
the end of the lecture,
please come back to
these learning objectives
and try to mind map all of
the different objectives
with what you've learned
throughout the slides.
Everything in today's
lecture maps back to Vanders
Renal Physiology, Chapters
6 and 7. This is available
for free online through
NYT's Medical Library,
which I included instructions
for on this slide.
You do not need the
textbook itself for the
materials that I cover in
this lecture, but I encourage
in case you want to
look through it for
yourself to see where I
get my points from, as well
as at the end of each
chapter, there are practice
questions that you can
use. I also used UWorld
to make sure that the
points I was bringing
up correlated towards
Bord's relevancy as well.
This lecture can be
broken down into three
parts. The first part,
I'm going to lay down
the foundational knowledge
of sodium and water
movement and why it
matters in terms of
maintaining cardiovascular
and renal homeostasis.
Then we're going to talk
about the regulation
of these movements in a
step-by-step manner in
Part 2. In Part 3, we're
going to explain why
dysregulation causes
certain disease states.
To start this lecture,
I have an opening
question which you
can pause and read.
We are going to revisit this
question at the
end of the lecture.
it describes a patient
who has congestive heart
failure, who is presenting
with signs of fluid
overload, as well as labs
showing low blood sodium.
So I want you to keep this
question in the back of
your mind as we go through
each of the parts and
start piecing together the
reasons mechanistically
why the kidney is contributing
to such a presentation
in heart failure let's
begin laying the foundation
by reviewing the body
fluid compartments we
know that 60 of body weight
is water two-thirds of
that being intracellular
fluid one-thirds being
extracellular fluid
extracellular fluid being further
broken down into
interstitial fluid and blood
plasma the main takeaway
of this slide is that ecf
and icf are an osmotic
equilibrium with each other.
Water will cross the
cell membranes freely
so that both compartments
will always reach
the same osmolality
level. Recall that
osmolarity and osmolality
are the same umbrella
term describing total
solute concentration.
Because your cells
contain NAK ATPase, your
intracellular sodium concentration
will be fairly stable,
but additions and
losses of sodium
will mostly occur
within the ECF.
Therefore, ECF is
the major osmol
which will influence
water movement.
So, if there's one
sentence that you guys
need to remember
from this slide, it's
where sodium moves,
water will follow.
Now let's talk about
reabsorption of sodium along the
nephron. Hopefully you
guys learned the different
segments of the nephron and what
takes place at each segment.
If not, these next few
slides should be sufficient
for your knowledge of sodium
and water reabsorption.
On the bottom right,
you'll see a nice flow that
describes the exact pathway
and steps for sodium
reabsorption, which we
will describe step by step.
First, sodium starts in
the tubular lumen, and
if it stays there, it
will be excreted as urine.
Sodium then crosses the
tubular wall actively
through apical transporters.
So remember, this is
an active transport process
in which sodium gets
reabsorbed. The transporter
on the apical wall
depends on the segment
that you're in the nephron.
Proximal tubule does your
bulk reabsorption of sodium,
which is about 65%, with
multiple transporters,
such as the sodium-hydrogen
antiport and the sodium
-glucose importer. The
descending limb has no
reabsorption of sodium, only
water. The thick ascending
limb is the opposite,
where there's only sodium
reabsorption and no water
reabsorption. Therefore, it's
known as the diluting segment,
and the apical transporter
is the sodium-potassium
chloride multiporter.
This is also the target
that loop diuretics use.
the DCT as the sodium
chloride symporter,
which is the target
of thiazide diuretics,
collecting duct as ENAC,
which is the apical
transporter that is fine
-tuned by aldosterone, which is
a key hormone that we will
discuss in this lecture.
Following this, sodium
will exit into the
interstitium basolaterally
through sodium potassium
ATPases, also through active
transport, and then it
reclaimed into a bloodstream
by entering nearby
capillaries, such as the
paratubular capillaries
and the vasorecta and
the medulla, the nephron.
Now we'll talk about
reabsorption of water along
the nephron in a deliberate
parallel to how we
discussed reabsorption
of sodium last slide.
You can see that the slides
are formatted similarly.
However, there are a
few key differences that
I need to highlight. In
step 2, you'll see that
water crosses the
tubule wall in a passive
manner through osmosis.
When before, with sodium,
sodium only crossed the
tubular wall actively
through specific
apical transporters.
In the proximal tubule,
water is freely permeable
and reabsorbed using
the aquaporin 1 channel,
and this is isoasmodic
bulk transport because
about 65% of sodium got
reabsorbed here, and what
does water like to do?
Water follows the sodium.
The descending thin limb
is permeable with aquaporin
1, but recall this
segment has no solute
reabsorption. The thick
ascending limb is the opposite,
where it's water impermeable
and only salt gets
reabsorbed here with and
KCC2. This is why the thick
ascending limb is known
as the diluting segment.
The collecting duct is
a unique area that has
permeability of water
controlled by ADH. So
when ADH is present, it
serves as an on switch,
bringing aquaporin
-2 channels to the
principal cells, allowing
for water reabsorption.
Then, when water is
reabsorbed, it moves down
its osmotic gradient
into the interstitium.
Recall last slide,
sodium needed NAK ATPase
to be pumped through
into the interstitium.
This time, water just
does it passively.
Then, water will enter the
nearby capillaries and will
be reclaimed into the
bloodstream. This slide goes
into further detail to explain
why ADH is so important
in the reabsorption of
water, and it falls under
this concept known as
countercurrent multiplication,
which I will describe
briefly in this lecture, but
there is more detail that
you will find in a future
lecture about it. So the main
concept is that the water
is separated from the salt
due to the loop of Henle.
Without this separation,
water would just
follow salt along
wherever it traveled.
The thick ascending
limb pumps salt
into the renal
medulla, creating a
hyperosmotic gradient
in the medulla.
Then at the collecting duct,
ADH is the main player deciding
if water gets reabsorbed
or not. If ADH is
present, you will have the
insertion of aquaporin-2
flowing water down the gradient
into that concentrated
medulum that we talked about.
If ADH is not present,
your tubule will stay
impermeable, and water can't
be reabsorbed, therefore
it's dilute. So this is
what allows the kidney
to control water excretion
independently of sodium,
and this also explains
why loop diuretics, which
control NKCC2 at this
thick ascending limb, are
so powerful at their
jobs of being a diuretic.
And here we have a summary
slide that shows this side
-by-side comparison and the
differences between sodium
reabsorption and water
reabsorption along the nephron.
And here is a nice summary
table that I made for you
guys for sodium and water
reabsorption along the
nephron segments, along
with some nice clinical
applications that you may see
while learning about renal
physiology I suggest that
you make your own table
similar to this and expand
it to the other lectures
that you're learning as
well so far in part one of
this lecture we've discussed
where the sodium and
water move now we need to
talk about why this matters
for the whole body and
that means we need to talk
about the cardiovascular
system the kidney and the
heart are locked in a
mutual dependency with one
another with the universal
goal being maintenance of
an effective blood circulation.
The kidney's job is
to filter blood, but in order
to do so, it is dependent
on the heart having
enough effective blood
pressure to reach the glomerulus
in order to push plasma
through the glomerulus so
blood can get filtered.
On the flip side, the kidney's
job is also to maintain
enough blood volume in
order for there to be enough
filling within the chambers
of the heart so the
heart has enough blood to
work with to pump out how does
the kidney maintain that
blood volume through control
of sodium and water so
the more sodium the kidney
decides to retain the more
water that will follow
and the more of ECF the blood
volume will increase and
therefore the vascular
system will be better filled
let me provide you with
enough cardiovascular
physiology to make renal
regulation make sense
effective blood circulation
as highlighted in the
red outlined box requires
two important factors
one enough pressure to
drive the blood forward
and two enough blood
volume to fill the vascular
system the pressure
needed to drive blood
forward depends on flow
which is otherwise known
as cardiac output and
resistance of the blood
vessels how well the
vessels constrict or relax
which we call total
peripheral resistance in terms
of an equation we call
this the mean arterial
pressure which is total
cardiac output times total
peripheral resistance flow
or cardiac output can be
further described as heart
rate times stroke volume.
Stroke volume is the blood
volume pumped per beat.
The total peripheral
resistance is defined by
constriction or relaxation
of the systemic arterioles
specifically. So when
the arterioles are
constricted, the vessel
radius is smaller therefore
there's more resistance
causing increased pressure
so pause and think about
this conceptually and try
to relate it to the
mathematical equations here
the second factor of this
harmonious relationship for
effective blood circulation
is having enough blood
volume in order to fill
the vascular system we know
blood volume is also known
as your plasma volume
within your extracellular
fluid and the main determinant
of this blood volume will
be your sodium and water
balance that is going to be
controlled by your kidney
as well as renally related
hormonal mechanisms
that we're going to talk
about in detail this lecture
some other factors are
ones that you can think of
pretty logically such as
fluid intake or restrictions
Other fluid losses,
such as sweating,
diarrhea, vomiting, or
fluid shifts like starling
forces in the case of low
albumin, for example, and
then also your red blood
cells play a part in the
blood volume. But I want
you to mostly hone in on
these renal and renally
related hormonal mechanisms.
That is the main
part of this lecture
that we are going
to be discussing.
Let's now summarize
this concept
in a fully integrated picture.
The kidneys through
sodium and water
balance are going to
influence the blood
volume. A higher blood
volume means more blood
is going to be
returning to the heart.
Therefore, you will have more
ventricular filling before
the heart takes a beat,
otherwise known as a higher
preload, which means you
will have an increased stroke
volume which is an increased
cardiac output second
your efferent arterials
are going to be controlling
resistance when they constrict
total peripheral resistance
increases blood pressure
is determined by both of
these factors MAP equals
cardiac output times tpr so
the kidneys mainly influence
cardiac output while the
arterioles mainly influence
resistance and together they
maintain organ perfusion
there's a very important
concept i need you guys to
remember and that's effective
circulating volume by
definition it's the portion of
arterial circulation that's
physically able to perfuse
your tissues otherwise how
much of circulating volume
is effective this is not
the same as the total
extracellular fluid volume
and you can think of it like
plumbing ecf is how much water
is actually in your pipes
but when you turn your sink
on effective circulating
volume is how much water
is able to reach the
taps or your organs in
parallel this is important
because your body can only
make changes on volume
based on what it's perceiving
and if your effective
circulating volume is low
your body might perceive
that as low volume which
we will discuss further
let's put part one
together with a question i
want you guys to pause
here read the question
and give your best answer based
on what you've learned so far
The correct answer is D.
This is the physiologic
basis of hypertension
and why a physician
might recommend
their patient to have
a low sodium diet.
Retaining sodium
causes water retention
because osmolality needs
to be held constant,
expanding the extracellular
fluid and plasma
volume, therefore
raising blood pressure.
Now we've made it
to how the body
is regulating those movements.
First, the body must sense
changes in water and sodium,
and it does that through
different receptors, such
as the baroreceptors, the
osmoreceptors, and the
macula densa. Then, the
body responds appropriately
through different hormonal
cascades, such as the RAS,
ADH, and natrietic
peptides. And there are
also protecting
stabilizers that are
important to keep the
front end steady so the
back end of the kidney
can be adjusted.
We're going to talk
about these step by step.
The kidney's goal of
sodium regulation is a
straightforward one that
has a lot of moving parts.
Essentially, the kidney
wants to keep 99% of sodium
reabsorption consistent,
And then that last 1% of
sodium, that's the part
that's going to get adjusted.
To do this, it wants to keep
the GFR, how much filtrate
is reaching the nephron,
the same, and then also
keep sodium delivery to the
distal nephron consistent.
This is why most of
your bulk reabsorption
of sodium happens
more proximally.
By keeping the proximal nephron
sodium condition steady,
the distal nephron
can be the adjustable
valve that matches output
and intake. This is
where your blood
volume, blood pressure,
through actions like
ADH and aldosterone, and
every diuretic drug
live, the distal nephron.
To understand blood
pressure control, you also
need to understand that
blood pressure control
is being handled by multiple
systems at different
time frames this table
summarizes the brief
overview in which we will
go into further detail
of in this lecture but
to quickly summarize
short-term seconds to
minutes will be your arterial
baroreflex which will be
stretch receptors in your
carotid sinus and aortic arch
that will change sympathetic
tone based on what it's
detecting in terms of stretch
intermediate minutes to
hours will specifically
be the angiotensin 2 actions
of ras which will engage
in constricting blood
vessels lastly your long-term
blood pressure control and
your ultimate blood volume
slash blood pressure in the
long run is controlled by
the kidney itself such as
through actions of aldosterone
which we will go over this
is why chronic hypertension
is treated as a kidney
volume problem here is
your short-term blood
pressure control the arterial
baroreceptors i will briefly
overview these in this
lecture but you will receive
more information about them
in your cardiovascular
physiology lectures later on
These are stretch-sensitive
mechanoreceptors that
will increase their firing
rate when they detect
increased blood pressure
through increased
arterial wall stretch.
You have two of them, one
in the aortic arch and
one in the carotid body.
When they detect that
increased blood pressure, they
will send signals through
their respective afferent
nerves into the medulla
and then the medulla
will modulate sympathetic
or parasympathetic output
in order to change blood
pressure in the short term
here's a side-by-side
comparison of what the
baroreceptors will do in
response to increased or
decreased blood pressure
or increased or decreased
arterial wall stretch on
the left side you will
see what the baroreceptor
does in response to an
increased arterial wall
stretch when that happens
the baroreceptors will
increase their firing rate
which in turn will tell
the medulla to decrease
sympathetic tone and
increase parasympathetic
outflow as a result you
will have vasodilation
and decreased heart
rate and contractility
ultimately leading to
blood pressure falling.
On the right side, when
you have decreased blood
pressure, it will be the opposite.
You will have an increased
sympathetic tone and
decreased parasympathetic
output, resulting in
vasoconstriction, increased heart rate
and heart contractility,
and blood pressure rising.
Note how these
are not affecting
the blood volume in any way.
rather it is just sympathetic
and parasympathetic
output being changed
in a short-term manner
besides the arterial
baroreceptors that we
just talked about there
are other vascular
baroreceptors in your
body as well that also
influence blood pressure
in some capacity
you have cardiopulmonary
baroreceptors that are located
on your heart as well as
your pulmonary vasculature
which will detect venous
filling so blood volume and
this is a big player in
influencing abh output when
blood volume is low which we
will talk about in further
detail towards the end
of the lecture intrarenal
baroreceptors are located at
the juxtaglomeria or granular
cells within the renal
afferent arterial over here
and this is important
because when it detects
low pressure it will
influence the release
of renin which begins
our discussion about
the renin angiotensin
aldosterone system
this slide is your
overview of the
renin angiotensin
aldosterone system
which we will talk about
step by step on the
following slides this system
turns on when the body
senses it is being under
filled or under perfused we
just talked about the
vascular baroreceptors that
live in your juxtaglomerular
apparatus that is
one of the examples that
helped switch on the RAS
system then when the RAS
system is turned on it
will defend arterial blood
pressure and effective
circulating volume to
homeostatic levels by retaining
salt and water and
constricting blood vessels.
I want you guys to pay
attention to the specific
members of the cast of
the RAS system and note
where each is made and
located within your body.
Angiotensinogen is the
precursor protein at the liver.
Renin is the enzyme from the
juxtaglomerular cells and
serves as the rate limiting
step of the RAS system.
Angiotensin one is an
inactive intermediate that
gets turned into angiotensin
two from ace angiotensin
converting enzyme ace
is located mainly on the
endothelium of the vessels
within your lung and then
finally the last step of
ras is aldosterone this is a
steroid hormone located
within your adrenal cortex
Part 1 of the RAS
walkthrough is understanding
what causes renin
to be released and
the conversions that
happen afterwards.
Renin is the rate-limiting
enzyme of your RAS
system and is released by
juxtaglomerular or granular
cells in response to
three specific triggers
that your juxtaglomerular
apparatus will detect.
First, you have sympathetic
beta-1 receptor nerve
fibers that can cause
the release of renin. You
also have the intrarenal
baroreceptors located
at the afferent arterial,
which we talked about,
as well as the macula
densa. The macula densa will
detect if sodium to the
distal convoluted tubule
is low and in response
cause release of renin.
From there, renin gets
released, and its job is
to cleave angiotensinogen,
this precursor enzyme,
into angiotensin 1.
And then angiotensin 1 is
converted to
angiotensin 2 by ACE.
Angiotensin 2 is one of
the main effector hormones
of the RAS system, which
we will talk about next
slide here are your actions
of angiotensin 2 it's a
peptide hormone that binds
to at1 receptors that perform
the following actions
pay attention to the ones
that are highlighted as
they are most significant
for blood pressure control
first it will vasoconstrict
systemic arterioles which
we learned increases the
total peripheral resistance
therefore increasing
blood pressure this is the
main mechanism of intermediate
blood pressure control
in the kidneys it's a
little bit different with how
it prefers vasoconstriction
angiotensin 2 will
constrict the efferent
arterial preferably over
the afferent arterial it'll
still constrict both but the
efferent a little bit more
due to the density of
at1 receptors the reason
this happens is it allows
the preservation of GFR which
we saw was one of our
goals of kidney regulation
furthermore angiotensin
2 works for sodium
reabsorption to increase
blood pressure by stimulating
several apical transporters
within the nephron
additionally it will
stimulate the release of
aldosterone the final
step of the RAS system
and finally it will also
talk to your brain to
increased factors such
as thirst, salt appetite,
sympathetic drive, and
release of ADH, all
further factors that will
contribute to increasing
blood volume and
therefore blood pressure.
The last effector to discuss
in the RAS is aldosterone.
Aldosterone is activated
by angiotensin II and is a
steroid hormone that binds to
intracellular mineralocorticoid
receptors to induce
transcriptional changes.
Because aldosterone is a
steroid hormone, it has
a longer duration of
effect. Therefore, it is one
of the main effectors in
long-term blood pressure
control versus angiotensin
2, which was a peptide
hormone that had a shorter
duration of effect.
The main action of aldosterone
for this lecture is
that it'll increase apical
ENAC and basolateral nik
atpases to increase sodium
reabsorption also aldosterone
increases potassium
excretion which is why it's
called the potassium waster
this is important because
certain diuretics that
target this area are known as
potassium sparing diuretics
which you will learn about
in your pharmacology
lecture another action of
aldosterone out of the scope
of this lecture but still
important for completeness
sake, is that it will increase
proton secretion by action
on intercollated cells.
An interesting fun fact
that I want to throw in here
is that glucocorticoids, such
as cortisol, can also bind
to the same receptor
aldosterone does, but normally
they are inactivated by
this enzyme called 11-beta
-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase,
don't remember that, which
protects the MR receptor for
aldosterone specifically.
for some reason if you eat
a lot of licorice it'll
inhibit that enzyme and
will cause an apparent
mineralocorticoid excess
that's just a fun fact for you
guys common theme you'll
start to notice in human
physiology is that
downstream effectors usually
serve as negative feedback
for the own initial steps
within their system so for
example here you can see
that angiotensin 2 production
will directly inhibit
the release of renin from
juxtaglomerular cells.
Also, what inhibits the RAS
system will be if the end
result has been reached,
therefore saying if intravascular
volume and blood pressure
is increased, that
will also serve as a trigger
to decrease renin release.
Of note, though,
if the underlying
deficit persists, a.k.a.
the body notices a
decreased effective
circulating volume, it
will cause the loop to keep
firing and renin to
keep being released,
which is known as
pathologic RAS activation.
Let's go over an example
of that in the next slide.
Renal artery stenosis is a
common condition that you
will see on board exams
because it challenges your
understanding on how RAS
activation works. What
happens is that there's a
narrowed or stenosed renal
artery caused by conditions
such as plaque buildup or
a unique condition called
fibromuscular dysplasia
and caused the kidney to
see low pressure or a low
ECV. This will cause chronic
renal release or pathologic
RAS activation, therefore
leading to chronic
hypertension. The classic
presentation is a patient
who presents with worsening
hypertension and they're
often on three or more
antihypertensives and their
blood pressure hasn't
improved in subsequent visits
this is a nice summary
flow chart i found of ras i
suggest you guys to make a
similar flow chart if that
works for you we talked
about negative feedback loops
for the ras system but there
are also peptides known
as natriatic peptides that
i like to call the anti
-ras so these are unique
atrial and brain natriatic
peptides because they're
released from cardiac myocytes
in response to increased
cardiac stretch the
actions will be the
opposite from ras to drive
sodium and water loss
also known as naturesis so
it'll dilate the
afferent arterial inhibit
renin and aldosterone
release and angiotensin's
reabsorption of sodium
and promote vasodilation
BNP or brain natriatic
peptide is interesting
because it will rise with
ventricular stretch and
is a key biomarker that
will be used in detecting
heart failure there are
some additional natrietic
factors that i included
for completeness sake
dopamine gets peripherally
converted from l-dopa
in the proximal tubule
and serves as a natrietic
paracrine signal to
reduce sodium reabsorption
endothelin also has natrietic
actions through unknown
mechanisms and even high
plasma potassium calcium can
act as a switch that will
inhibit sodium reabsorption
recall the goals of
regulation of the kidney which
i have here again on the
top right we want to keep
the gfr steady and the 99
percent of sodium that gets
reabsorbed consistent therefore
that final one percent
can be delivered to the
distal nephron and be adjusted
appropriately there are
three intra renal guardians
that I have here to protect
goals 1 and 2 of the
kidney the first being
prostaglandins prostaglandins are
released by your macula
densa cells in response to
angiotensin 2 remember
what angiotensin 2 does it
vasoconstricts the efferent
and the afferent arterioles
although it prefers the
efferent more in response
prostaglandins will dilate the
afferent arterial so now we
have the efferent constricted
and the afferent dilated
the reason that prostaglandins
do this is to keep
your renal blood flow and
gfr steady matching goal 1
this also explains why
NSAIDs can potentially cause
acute kidney injury if you
have NSAIDs inhibiting the
synthesis of prostaglandins
in a patient whose volume
depleted and has angiotensin
2 acting it will cause
unopposed afferent constriction
and therefore your GFR
will crash and you will
have an acute kidney injury.
The final two intrarenal
guardians sound
pretty similar but act
in opposite directions.
Tubuloglomerular feedback
is your tubular feedback to
your glomerulus to change
the glomerular output. This
is done by the macula densa
at the DCT. If it senses
high salt it's a sign that
your GFR is high so it will
tell the afferent arterial
to constrict to lower that
GFR back to normal protecting
goal one that we talked
about glomerular tubular
balance or GTB goes like this
whatever your GFR is your
proximal tubule will always
match that so if your gfr
rises 20 for any reason your
proximal tubule will
reabsorb the same fraction of
whatever is filtered therefore
you have a balance in
sodium reabsorption and match
goal 2 of renal regulation
this is a summary table
talking about the changes
within glomerular
filtration rate renal blood
flow, and filtration fraction
with respect to changes
in afferent and efferent
renal arterial dilation
or constriction. I wanted
to include this just
for a synthetic purpose
and as a supplement to
Kyle's GFR lecture. Shout
out to my good friend.
So far, we've spent
most of part two on the
way the body will adjust
volume through sodium,
RAS,
and intrarenal guardians.
Now, we're going to talk
about how when the kidney
detects abnormal concentration
or osmolality, it
will adjust water via ADH,
antidiuretic hormone. Recall
when we talk osmolality
that is what's going to
track sodium the goal of
water excretion is to keep
the plasma osmolality
within the normal range of
275 to 295 as well as serum
sodium within 135 to 145
while preserving the
vascular volume that ras is
defending retain more water
you dilute osmolality excrete
more water you concentrate
it water sets concentration
so how does ADH act when
it detects changes in
osmolality it is produced
by a hypothalamic super
optic or paraventricular
nuclei and secreted it into
the bloodstream by the
posterior pituitary gland the
action is to insert aquaporin
2 into the collecting
duct to promote water
reabsorption so if ADH is up,
you will have a low volume
urine because more water
is being reabsorbed. And
if more water is being
reabsorbed, it will dilute the
serum sodium concentration.
Therefore, it will fall
back to a normal level.
The opposite is true. If
ADH is low, you will have a
dilute high volume urine
because less water is being
reabsorbed and your serum
sodium levels will rise.
At high levels,
ADH also acts on V1
receptors as a
vasoconstrictor. This is
why ADH also has a
name vasopressin.
On the right box, you will
see some clinical correlates
that you will see multiple
times throughout your
med school career, but I
wanted to highlight them now.
Too much ADH is called
symptom of inappropriate
antidiuretic hormone, which is
where you're having continuous
water retention, therefore
hyponatremia. Too little
ADH or ineffective ADH
response is known as diabetes
insipidus, which is water
loss and hypernatremia.
So far in our discussion
of ADH, I've been
harping on the fact that
the main way your body
senses changes and
triggers ADH release is
through changes in
osmolality. This is true
for normal conditions
in your day-to-day life.
You have osmoreceptors that
are located within your
brain that will detect
changes in plasma osmolality
or sodium concentration and
cause the release of ADH.
However, you also have
baroreceptors, your
cardiopulmonary,
and your arterial
baroreceptors that play
a role in ADH release.
Specifically, this role
is in emergency situations
when your body is losing
a lot of blood volume.
Your baroreceptors will
actually take over as
the main sensory input
to trigger ADH release.
This makes sense because
if you're losing critical
levels of blood volume,
the best way to maintain
a blood volume is to put
as much water in your body
as you can and what
better to do that than adh
let's talk about that in
further detail next slide
as we discussed normal
conditions osmoreceptors
rule we want this to be
the case because adh works
best when you are
reabsorbing water in order to
balance levels of plasma
sodium and osmolality.
However,
under critical conditions,
such as a massive hemorrhage,
there's a different story.
Here, you want to
maintain as much
blood volume as
possible to stay alive.
So, your baroreceptors
take over
and override the
osmoreceptor input,
triggering your body to release
as much ADH as possible.
This is because you
want to maintain as
much blood volume as
you can keep those
organs perfused and
hopefully stay alive
however there is a major
trade-off that the body must
sacrifice in order to do
this and that is because
you are retaining water in
excess and overriding the
osmo receptors there is
no adjustment that can be
made to sodium so sodium will
fall causing hyponatremia
hopefully when you make
it to the hospital, they
will correct those sodium
levels for you over time.
Interestingly enough, to
reopen our conversation about
effective circulating
volume, this dangerous volume
drop can be falsely perceived
by your body as a low
ECV and cause ADH to be
released inappropriately as
well additional regulators of
adh that i find interesting
are angiotensin 2 which
makes sense because
angiotensin itself will be
activated under low volume
states so you will want
adh to play along with that
other triggers are pain
severe stress nausea vomiting
these are all examples of
non-osmotic triggers along
with the baroreceptor
trigger that we talked about
alcohol also
inhibits adh causing
that high volume dilute urine
it wouldn't be a lecture
about sodium and water
without talking about
your appetite for them
because your kidneys can
only do so much you need to
actually put salt and water
in your body in order to
compensate for changes
that are being made so we
talked about angiotensin
2 being a trigger for salt
appetite and thirst but
there are also triggers that
make sense like reduced
plasma volume and increased
serum osmolality as well as
the feeling of a dry mouth
i included this slide
here for completeness sake
so you have a whole picture
of the three timescales
of blood pressure control
that we talked about
which aligns with learning
objective number four
in our lecture please don't
freak out when you see
all of these words rather
pause read them along
and see if they
make sense to you
we've made it to the
final part of this lecture
where we are going to
apply everything we've
learned so far and
integrate it into a very
fascinating condition
known as heart failure.
Heart failure occurs
for several reasons
out of the scope of
this lecture. However,
the theme is the same. The
heart muscles are weakened
and there is a weak pump.
With a weak pump, you
are unable to deliver
enough blood to the arteries
and not enough blood is
able to reach your tissues.
Therefore,
you have a decreased
effective circulating volume.
This decreased effective
circulating volume will
cause your body to
recognize it as low volume.
Therefore,
sensors such as your
intra renal baroreceptors
will trigger release
of RAS, sympathetics,
antidiuretic hormone, and
cause the kidney to retain
sodium and water. This
results in total body
volume increasing your
extracellular fluid volume,
causing many of the signs
and symptoms that you see
in heart failure on the
right side of your screen,
such as pitting edema on
the lower extremities,
ascites, and pulmonary edema.
However, the theme stays
the same the pump is
still weak therefore your
effective circulating
volume never recovers
still low because of this
a vicious cycle happens
where your body will
still perceive as low
volume and trigger RAS
sympathetics and ADHD
continuously although we
discussed natriotic
peptides being the anti-RAS.
The effects we discussed
last slide of RAS
and sympathetics are too
vicious and too prominent
for the natriotic
peptides to overcome.
BNP is often used as a severity
marker in heart failure.
Hyponatremia is another
severity marker where if it's
present in a heart failure
patient it often indicates
higher risk of mortality
this is because of the ECV
being so low that it triggers
the non-osmotic release
of antidiuretic hormone
similar to the baroreceptor
trigger that we talked about
previously for ADH release
pharmacologically we
attempt to treat our failure
by calming down the
kidneys over firing signals
we will use loop diuretics
acutely to reduce
total body volume we
will use aces and arbs to
lower angiotensin 2 mr
antagonists to lower
aldosterone and sometimes
sucubitril in combination
to increase the level
of natriotic peptide.
I want you guys
now to revisit the
opening question
of this lecture.
See if you can answer
the following questions
that we discussed
in the next slide.
Here is the opening
question revisited.
Hopefully now you can answer
the following three questions.
if the patient is fluid
overloaded wires kidneys acting
like he's dehydrated by
retaining more salt and
water this is because the
kidney defends effective
circulating volume which is
low in heart failure despite
high total volume if he's
retaining salt and water
why is the sodium low because
of the barrel receptor
override mechanism that we
discussed driving ADH and
a non-osmotic trigger that's
why hyponatremia is often
a signal of high mortality
why do we treat them
with drugs that act on the
kidney for a heart problem
because the damage is being
done through inappropriate
signaling to the kidney that
low effective circulating
volume so we attempt to
switch those signals off
thank you all again for
sticking through it with me
in this lecture this is
one of my favorite topics
in medicine because it shows
you how well integrated
the body is and all the
small moving parts that
come together for one
overarching goal of maintaining
blood volume and blood
pressure please contact
me at any time with any
questions through my email
i'll always be happy
to provide any kind of
knowledge or mentorship
that i can or redirect
you to the best source
for them you guys are
all amazing best of
luck in your medical
journeys and have a
wonderful rest of your day.